From the Emirati perspective, the Mecca
Pact is therefore clearly a challenge.
What is less clear is how Abu Dhabi will
try to counter it. By repairing ties
with Riyadh or by moving even closer to
Israel. At this stage, the second option
appears more likely.
The agreement also complicates Saudi
Arabia's relationship with India. Riyadh
certainly has no intention of abandoning
its close economic and energy ties with
New Delhi. But formal commitments to
Pakistan will make it harder for the
kingdom to remain neutral during the
next India-Pakistan crisis.
At the same time, India has developed
close partnerships with Israel and the
UAE and is part of the IMEC corridor
project, which is intended to connect
India with Europe through the Persian
Gulf and Israel. The Mecca Pact
therefore sharpens an existing
contradiction in Indian strategy between
its growing relationship with Gulf
states on the one hand and its strategic
partnership with Israel and rivalry with
Pakistan on the other.